Ata Kalirad, PhD

Postdoctoral research fellow
Max-Planck-Institut für Biologie Tübingen
Department for Integrative Evolutionary Biology
Max-Planck-Ring 9
72076 Tübingen, Germany

E-mail: ata.kalirad@tuebingen.mpg.de
Web: https://kalirad.github.io/info.github.io/.
http://www.sommerlab.org/research/evolutionary-genomics-and-bioinformatics.html

Research

My current research revolves around understanding the importance of <u>phenotypic plasticity</u> in evolution and the causes of <u>environmental robustness</u> using different species of *Pristionchus* - a genus of nematodes - at Ralf Sommer's lab in Tübingen. In addition, I utilise toy models, such as computational model of RNA folding, to investigate evolutionary questions.

Academic Positions

March 2020 - Present Postdoctoral Fellow, Department for Integrative Evolutionary Biology, Max-Planck-Institut

für Biologie Tübingen, Tübingen, Germany

Past Academic Positions

Feb 2019 - Feb 2020 Postdoctoral Fellow, Institute for Research in Fundamental Sciences (IPM), Tehran, Iran
Oct 2017 - Jan 2018 Research Fellow, Institute for Research in Fundamental Sciences (IPM), Funded by Iran's

National Elites Foundation

Education

2011 - Dec 2016 PhD, Department of Biology and Biochemistry, University of Houston, TX, USA 2008 - 2011 BSc, Department of Biology, University of Tehran, Iran

Publications

2021

A. Kalirad and R. J. Sommer, *The art of mechanistic modeling in biology*, Nature Computational Science, doi: https://doi.org/10.1038/s43588-021-00187-9

M. Dardiry, V. Piskobulu, **A. Kalirad**, and R. J. Sommer, *Experimental and theoretical support for costs of plasticity and phenotype in a nematode cannibalistic trait*, bioRxiv, doi: https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.02.28.482339

J. W. Lightfoot, M. Dardiry, **A. Kalirad**, S. Giaimo, G. Eberhardt, H. Witte, M. Wilecki, C.

Rödelsperger, A. Traulsen, R. J. Sommer, Sex or cannibalism: Polyphenism and kin recognition control social action strategies in nematodes, Science Advances,

doi: 10.1126/sciadv.abg8042

- H. Safdari, **A. Kalirad**, and M. Sadeghi, *Population-level heterogeneity as a reflection of mixed strategy: A computational perspective on the Crabtree effect*, Journal of Theoretical Biology, doi: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtbi.2021.110912 (Co-first author)
- S. Vafadar, M. Shahdoust, **A. Kalirad**, P. Zakeri, and Mehdi Sadeghi, *Competitive exclusion during co-infection as a strategy to prevent the spread of a virus: a computational perspective*, PLOS ONE, doi: https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0247200 (All author contributed equally)

2020

- H. Safdari, **A. Kalirad**, C. Picioreanu, R. Tusserkani, B. Goliaei, M. Sadeghi, *Noise-driven cell differentiation and the emergence of spatiotemporal patterns*, PLOS ONE, doi: https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0232060 (Co-first author)
- S. Vafadar, K. Kavousi, H. Safdari, **A. Kalirad**, M. Sadeghi, *From indication to decision: A hierarchical approach to model the chemotactic behavior of Escherichia coli*, Journal of Theoretical Biology, doi: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtbi.2020.110253

2016

A. Kalirad and R. B. R. Azevedo, *Spiralling complexity: a test of the snowball effect in a computational model of RNA folding*, Genetics, doi: https://doi.org/ 10.1101/076232. 2017 (chosen by the editors as one of the May 2017 Highlights)

2011

H. Asgharian, E. Elahi, **A. Kalirad**, and H. Hosseinzadeh Saha, Sequence data on four genes suggest nominal Gerres lamentosus specimens from Nayband National Park in the Persian Gulf represent two distinct species, Iranian Journal Of Animal Biosystematics 6(2): 1-11.

Books

2021

How to Tame a Fox (and Build a Dog), Lee Dugatkin & Lyudmila Trut, Translated into Farsi by Ata Kalirad, Fatemi Publication, Tehran (authorized translation)

Other Professional Positions

2018 - Present	Member of the Genetics & Biotechnology Committee at the Academy of Persian
	Language and Literature, Tehran, Iran
2017 - 2020	Member of the Scientific Committee for the Iranian Biology Olympiad (irBO) at the
	National Center for Development of Exceptional Talents, Tehran, Iran
2017 - 2018	Member of the Scientific Committee for the 29th International Biology Olympiad (IBO),
	Tehran, Iran

Teaching

Courses

2019 Species and speciation, Graduate-level course, University of Tehran, School of Biology (Department

of Zoological Sciences), Spring 2019

General Biology 2, Undergraduate-level course, University of Tehran, School of Biology (Department

of Biotechnology), Spring 2019

2017 - 2020 Teaching various courses on evolution at the National Center for Development of Exceptional

Talents, Tehran, Iran